Hello everybody and welcome to another
walkthrough and this time we're going to
do some walkthrough
in the CDC 6504 machine language emulator.
So let's first just talk a little bit
about all the
things that we can do here. So this is
kind of our machine language emulator. We
have a series
of instructions. It starts out all zeros.
We have data memory. We have 256
instructions. We have 256
data memories. We have an accumulator
register, an X register, and a Y register
taken from the 6502.
And then we have the program counter which
points to where we're at. Our program
counter currently
says zero pointing at instruction memory
zero. The Z is a flag that once we do a
calculation or store
some stuff, it'll and the result of that
is a zero. The Z will check and N stands
for negative.
So you can you can branch if negative,
branch if positive, branch if zero.
And so
these are
used to do a pattern of compare then
branch. Um we can load a program from
here. Let's just load
a simple sample so you can see it. Um you
can also view the assembly language. And
so what I'll tend
to do is I'll tend to put the assembly
language over here. And um and then I've
got this narrate
execution. You can hover over each of the
memory locations and it tells you for
example that this
0x0 location is a E2 and hex and it is a
clear instruction. Now sometimes this is
instruction,
sometimes it's data when we're doing load
immediates. So this it it tells you you
know if it's ASKY it'll tell you what the
ASKY character is. Um and so it has to
interpret this
but this is just zeros and ones in the
computer memory and it's contextualized
what's going on.
So this is just a clear instruction. Oops. A
clear instruction, an increment instruction,
and an increment instruction. And then a
break, which is just a zero,
which stops
the thing
from running. And we can see the same thing
right here in the assembly line. It's clear,
increment, increment, break. Eventually,
we're going to want to just look at the
assembly. It
just makes our lives a lot simpler to
watch what's going on. Um, but reality,
it's zeros and ones.
Um and so we have a couple of uh options
here. We can start the application. We can
run it a single
step. Uh and we can reset it. But that
clears everything and we got to load a new
program.
But we have this cool feature called
narrate execution. And it slows it down
and describes
everything that's going on. And so I'm
going to tell you in advance what's going
to happen. It's
going to clear the X register. And you got
to watch the X register here.
Then it's
going to
add one to the X register. Watch the X
register. and then add one again to the X
register. And when
it's all said and done, it'll stop and
nothing else will have changed except the
Cure X register
will have a two in it. So, I'm going to move
this over here and you can kind of watch as
the program counter moves along and just
kind of that assembly is there for you to
remember. Now,
later you can write assembly and get it
assembled. So, let me go ahead. It's got
narrate execution turned on and let me
start it. PC 0 PC01 increment X register
PC0X02 increment
X register PC0X03 break no printed output.
Okay, so you saw what happened there. Um,
let me go and do this a little more
slowly. Let me reload it. Load simple
sample. And I'm going
to instead when we narrate execution, I'm
going to hit step. So you saw it run
automatically. And
so I'm going to do step. So it's going to
run one instruction and narrate it when I
press step. PC0.
Okay. So notice that the Z flag now the
and it's a it's a one one bite
instruction. So the PC went up
by one. The Z flag is now set. It's not a
negative number because the X register is
a zero which is
not negative. And that is the result of that
particular instruction. So let's step again.
PC01 increment X register. So we
incremented X. So if we look at X, X has
now gone from zero to one.
The program counter is ready for the next
instruction. But because X is
now one,
neither the
Z nor the N flag is set. So let's step one
more time. PC0x2 increment X register.
Okay. So now
the PC the next register that we're going
the next instruction is going to be 0x03
and the X register
is two. The Z and the N flags are set
accordingly. When we step again, we're
going to hit this break,
which is a stop. And then the program
execution break, no printed output. And
what it's talking
about no printed output is in future ones,
we put some data. When we put data in here,
the printed output comes out of the first
few up to a zero bite in the memory. But
this one has no
particular memory. Okay. So, let's just
take a look at a couple of other things
that we have.
It has a bunch of documentation. It's
pretty cool. It's uh it's
probably more
you can read
this. AI can read this. It's pretty cool.
That's just a URL that you can go paste
into AI if you
want and you can ask AI for help writing
this code. Um we'll see how well
AI does
with this,
but it has documentation. We also need an
asky chart, right? I have this is not a
text one. So,
but we have a little asky chart that tells
the space is 32 decimal. It's 20 hex and
00 1 0 0.
And remember that that hex you can do a 4bit
to one column hex to binary conversion. And
and for me I start seeing things like I'll
look at like this one here. I know that's
a seven. So
that's 27. Um I'll see this 111. And I'll
see that as an F. So you'll start
to see
hopefully
after a while you'll kind of have a hex
tobinary conversion in your me in your
mind. decimal is a
pain in the neck. You got I just got to hand
convert both decimal to hex and binary. And
so that's pretty much all of the features
of the application. And so next we're
going to go through
uh some of these things in a little bit
more detail. Um, and so, uh, we'll come to
those in a